Register of the Jeanne Marie Valentine Lambrino Papers, 1916-1956.
Hoover Institution Archives
Jeanne Marie Valentine Lambrino Papers
1916-1956
73075
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (0.9 linear feet)
Memoirs, diaries, letters, notes, clippings, and photographs, relating to the marriage of J. M. V. Lambrino with Prince Carol and its subsequent annulment. Includes a diary about Prince Carol, 1919-1920.
Lambrino, Jeanne Marie Valentine, 1895?-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note.
1895? Born in Roman, Rumania
1918, 31 August Married Carol, Prince of Rumania
1919, March 29 Marriage annulled
1920, January 8 Son, Mircea Carol, born
Carol II, King of Romania, 1893-1953.; Romania--History.; Romania.
- WRITINGS
  Scope and Contents note
  Memoirs of Zizi Lambrino.
  - Memoirs of Zizi Lambrino (four drafts in typescript, and three in handwriting), for her book Mon Marie, Le Roi Carol. Paris, C. Levy (1950). 168 p. (Box 1)
- DIARIES, 1916-1921
  Diaries of Zizi Lambrino. Diary about Carol, Prince of Rumania.
  - 6 diaries of Zizi Lambrino, 1916-1921 (in handwriting) (Box 1-2.)
  - Diary about Carol, Prince of Rumania, December 14, 1919- December 6, 1920 (in handwriting) (Box 2)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1916?-1956
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Bratianu, C., letter to Zizi Lambrino, 28 January 1926 (Box 2)
  - Carol, Prince of Rumania
    - Letters from Carol to Zizi Lambrino, 1917-1920 (with enclosures)
    - Letters from Zizi Lambrino to Carol, 1916?-1921
  - Ciocardia?, Georges, letters and postcards from "Georges" to Zizi Lambrino
  - Condeescu, General Adjutant N., letters to Zizi Lambrino, 1921
  - Cosacescu, J., letter to Zizi Lambrino, 9 August 1956
  - Dixon, T., letter to Carol (Mircea Carol, Zizi Lambrino's son), 21 August 1956
  - Eulalia, Princess of Spain, letters to Zizi Lambrino from Eulalia, Infanta of Spain, 1938-1953
  - Forrez, M., letter to Zizi Lambrino, 14 March 1926
  - Godart, L., letter to Zizi Lambrino, 9 March 1926
  - Jensen, Mrs. Lloyd, letter to Zizi Lambrino, 17 August 1921
  - Lamart, ? de, letter to Dr. Lund, Brazil
  - Lambrino, Euphrosine Letters from Zizi Lambrino to her mother, 1919-1920; Letters from Carol to Mrs. E. Lambrino, 1917
  - Lambrino, Loulou Letters from Zizi Lambrino to her brother "Loulou" Military postcards from Loulou to Zizi Lambrino
  - Lambrino, Mircea Carol, letter from Zizi Lambrino to her son Mircea Carol, 25 August 1947
  - Marie, Queen of Rumania
    - Letter from Carol to his mother, July 1919
    - Letter from Zizi Lambrino to Queen Marie, 1 July 1928
    - Letter and thank-you note from Queen Marie to "Madame (E.?) Lambrino" (Zizi's mother)
  - S. Marie Mathildes deTroy?, letters to Zizi Lambrino, 12 July 1914; 2 April 1916
  - Masouko, letters to Zizi Lambrino, 1950?
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: letters, telegrams, postcards, (undentified)
  - Nicolae, Prince of Rumania (brother of Carol), letters to Zizi Lambrino, 1917 (signed "Nicolae")
- MISCELLANY
  Certificates, poems, clippings, calling cards, and miscellaneous printed matter, arranged as listed.
  - Certificates; copy of annulment contract to marriage of Zizi and Carol, 3 July 1921; handwritten copies of letters (Box 2)
  - "Toi et Moi," poems by Paul Geraldy, booklet (copies in handwritten) with the inscription "Atroi! Souvenir d'epreuve, Signe d'esperance! Tassay 1918, Carol."
  - Three printed items on Rumania:
    - Observations Concerning the Draft Peace Treaty with Roumania, Paris 1946
    - "Realisations Sociales en Roumanie; la verite sur les reforms actuelles comparee aux resultats obtenus avant 1938," 1946
    - Beza, Marcu. Bessarabia and Transylvania. 1940
  - Miscellaneous clippings, calling cards, etc.
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  15 photographs of Zizi Lambrino, her mother, her son Mircea Carol with his child, and others.